I believe that the secret to producing extremely drought-tolerant crops,
أنا أؤمن بأن السر في إنتاج المحاصيل شدبدة التحمل للجفاف،
which should go some way to providing food security in the world,
والتي يجب أن تتقدم لتوفر الأمن الغذائي في العالم،
lies in resurrection plants,
تكمن في النباتات القابلة للنشور،
pictured here, in an extremely droughted state.
المصورة هنا في حالة الجفاف الشديد.
You might think that these plants look dead,
و قد يخطر لك أن هذه النباتات تبدو ميتة،
but they're not.
ولكنها ليست كذلك.
Give them water,
أعطها الماء،
and they will resurrect, green up, start growing, in 12 to 48 hours.
و ستقوم بالنشور و الأخضرار و النمو خلال 12 إلى 48 ساعة.
Now, why would I suggest
والآن، لماذا أقترح
that producing drought-tolerant crops will go towards providing food security?
بتقديم المحاصيل شديدة التحمل للجفاف لتوفير الأمن الغذائي؟
Well, the current world population is around 7 billion.
حسنا، إن عدد سكان العالم حاليا حوالي 7 مليارات.
And it's estimated that by 2050,
ومن المخمن بأننا في عام 2050،
we'll be between 9 and 10 billion people,
سنكون بين 9 و 10 مليارات من السكان،
with the bulk of this growth happening in Africa.
وسيكون الحجم الأكبر لهذا النمو في إفريقيا
The food and agricultural organizations of the world
وقد اقترحت منظمات الغذاء والزراعة في العالم
have suggested that we need a 70 percent increase
بأننا نحتاج إلى زيادة 70%
in current agricultural practice
في الممارسات الزراعية الحالية
to meet that demand.
للاستجابة لذلك الطلب.
Given that plants are at the base of the food chain,
و بما أن النباتات هي أساس السلسلة الغذائية،
most of that's going to have to come from plants.
فإن معظم هذه الزيادة يجب أن تأتي من الزراعة.
does not take into consideration the potential effects of climate change.
لا تأخذ بالاعتبار التأثير الكامن للتغيير المناخي.
This is taken from a study by Dai published in 2011,
هذا مقتبس من دراسة نشرها داي في 2011،
where he took into consideration
حيث أخذ بنظر الاعتبار
all the potential effects of climate change
كل التأثيرات الكامنة للتغيير المناخي
and expressed them -- amongst other things --
و عبّر عنها - ضمن أشياء أخرى -
increased aridity due to lack of rain or infrequent rain.
بتزايد الجفاف لفقدان الأمطار أو تقطعها.
The areas in red shown here,
المناطق الحمراء الظاهرة هنا
are areas that until recently
هي مناطق كانت مؤخرا و قبل فترة قصيرة
have been very successfully used for agriculture,
تستخدم بنجاح تام للزراعة،
but cannot anymore because of lack of rainfall.
ولكن لا يمكن ذلك الآن بسبب فقدان الأمطار.
This is the situation that's predicted to happen in 2050.
و هذا هو الوضع متوقع حدوثه في 2050.
Much of Africa, in fact, much of the world,
و الكثير من أفريقيا و كذلك الكثير من العالم،
is going to be in trouble.
سيكون واقعا في مشكلة.
We're going to have to think of some very smart ways of producing food.
يجب علينا أن نفكر لنجد بعض الطرق الذكية جدا لإنتاج الغذاء
And preferably among them, some drought-tolerant crops.
و يفضل أن يكون ضمنها، بعض المحاصيل المقاومة للجفاف.
The other thing to remember about Africa is
و الشيء الآخر الذي يجب أن نتذكر عن أفريقيا
that most of their agriculture is rainfed.
هو أن أكثر زراعتهم تعتمد على المطر.
Now, making drought-tolerant crops is not the easiest thing in the world.
ولكن، زراعة المحاصيل المقاومة للجفاف ليست أسهل شيء في العالم.
And the reason for this is water.
و السبب في هذا هو الماء.
Water is essential to life on this planet.
الماء أساسي للحياة على هذا الكوكب.
All living, actively metabolizing organisms,
كل الأحياء والكائنات الحية،
from microbes to you and I,
من الميكروبات إليك و إليّ،
are comprised predominately of water.
يتكون أغلبها من الماء.
All life reactions happen in water.
كل ردود فعل الحياة تحدث في الماء.
And loss of a small amount of water results in death.
و فقدان القليل من الماء ينتج عنه الموت.
You and I are 65 percent water --
أنا وأنت نتكون من 65% ماء --
we lose one percent of that, we die.
وإذذا فقدنا 1% من ذلك نموت.
But we can make behavioral changes to avoid that.
ولكننا نستطيع إجراء بعض التغييرات السلوكية لتجنب ذلك.
Plants can't.
أما النباتات فلا تستطيع.
They're stuck in the ground.
فهي ملتصقة بالأرض.
about 95 percent water,
أي إن الماء فيها حوالي 95%،
and they can lose a little bit more than us,
وتستطيع أن تفقد منه قليلا أكثر منا،
like 10 to about 70 percent, depending on the species,
أي بين 10 إلى 70% حسب نوعها،
but for short periods only.
ولكن لفترات قليلة فقط.
Most of them will either try to resist or avoid water loss.
وغالبيتها ستقاوم أو تتجنب خسارة الماء.
So extreme examples of resistors can be found in succulents.
وهكذا نجد المثال الأقصى لهذه المقاومة في النباتات المقاومة للجفاف.
They tend to be small, very attractive,
فهي تميل لأن تكون صغيرة و جذابة جدا،
but they hold onto their water at such great cost
ولكنها تتمسك بالماء فيها بكلفة عالية
that they grow extremely slowly.
كما إأها تنمو ببطء شديد جدا.
Examples of avoidance of water loss are found in trees and shrubs.
و نجد في الأعشاب والأشجار أمثلة على تجنب فقدان الماء.
They send down very deep roots,
فهي ترسل جذورها عميقا،
mine subterranean water supplies
و تلتمس مواقع المياه الجوفية
and just keep flushing it through them at all times,
و تستمر باستخدامها بواسطتها دائما،
keeping themselves hydrated.
و تبقي نفسها مرتوية.
The one on the right is called a baobab.
التي إلى اليمين تسمى (باوباب).
simply because the proportion of roots to shoots is so great
ببساطة لأن نسبة حجم الجذور إلى الجزء الظاهر كبيرة جدا
that it looks like the tree has been planted upside down.
مما يجعلها تبدو و كأنها زرعت بالمقلوب.
And of course the roots are required for hydration of that plant.
و بالطبع فإن الجذور مطلوبة لإرواء النبتة.
And probably the most common strategy of avoidance is found in annuals.
ويمكن أن تكون للحوليات السنوية أكثر استراتيجية مشتركة لتجنب الفقدان.
Annuals make up the bulk of our plant food supplies.
و تشكل الحوليات غالبية النباتات التي تعطينا غذائنا.
Up the west coast of my country,
على الساحل الغربي من بلادي،
for much of the year you don't see much vegetation growth.
لا تشاهد نمو الكثير من النباتات في أكثر مواسم السنة .
But come the spring rains, you get this:
ولكن عندما تاتي أمطار الربيع تحصل على هذا:
flowering of the desert.
ازدهار الصحراء.
The strategy in annuals,
إن استراتيجية الحوليات السنوية،
is to grow only in the rainy season.
هي النموفقط في مواسم المطر.
At the end of that season they produce a seed,
وفي نهاية ذلك الموسم فإنها تنتج بذرة،
which is dry, eight to 10 percent water,
تكون جافة و تحتوي 8 إلى 10 بالمائة ماءا،
but very much alive.
ولكنها حية تماما.
And anything that is that dry and still alive,
وأي شيء يكون جافا هكذا و يبقى حيا،
we call desiccation-tolerant.
نسميه قابلا للبقاء جافا.
In the desiccated state,
وفي حالة البقاء جافة،
what seeds can do is lie in extremes of environment
ما ستفعل البذرة هو البقاء في بيئة متطرفة
for prolonged periods of time.
لفترة طويلة من الزمن.
The next time the rainy season comes,
و عندما يبدأ الموسم الممطر ثانية ،
they germinate and grow,
فهي تنبت و تنمو،
and the whole cycle just starts again.
وتبدأ دورة حياتها من جديد كاملة.
It's widely believed that the evolution of desiccation-tolerant seeds
و من المقبول أن تطور البذور المتحملة للجفاف
allowed the colonization and the radiation
سمحت بتوسع وانتشار
of flowering plants, or angiosperms, onto land.
النباتات المزهرة أو بذورها على الارض.
But back to annuals as our major form of food supplies.
ولكن لنعد إلى الحوليات التي هي مصدر غذائنا الرئيسي.
Wheat, rice and maize form 95 percent of our plant food supplies.
القمح والرز والذرة تشكل 95 بالمائة من مصادر كوكبنا للغذاء.
And it's been a great strategy
وقد كان ذلك ستراتيجية عظيمة
because in a short space of time you can produce a lot of seed.
لأنك تتمكن من إنتاج الكثير من البذور في وقت قصير.
Seeds are energy-rich so there's a lot of food calories,
والبذور غنية بالطاقة أي بالكثير من سعرات الغذاء الحرارية
you can store it in times of plenty for times of famine,
ويمكن أن تخزنها عندما تفيض لأوقات القحط،
but there's a downside.
ولكن هناك أجزاء ستتلف.
The vegetative tissues,
كالأنسجة النباتية،
the roots and leaves of annuals,
والجذور والأوراق الحولية،
do not have much
ليس لها الكثير
by way of inherent resistance, avoidance or tolerance characteristics.
من المقاومة الكامنة وخواص التجنب والتحمل.
They just don't need them.
لأنها ببساطة لا تحتاجها.
They grow in the rainy season
فهي تنمو في موسم الأمطار
and they've got a seed to help them survive the rest of the year.
و لديها بذرة تساعدها على البقاء حية لبقية العام.
And so despite concerted efforts in agriculture
لذا و على الرغم من الجهود القائمة
to make crops with improved properties
لجعل المحاصيل ذات خواص محسنة
of resistance, avoidance and tolerance --
للمقاومة والتجنب و التحمل --
particularly resistance and avoidance
و خاصة المقاومة والتجنب
because we've had good models to understand how those work --
لأن لدينا نماذج جيدة لفهم كيفية عملها --
we still get images like this.
لكننا لا نزال نتلقى صورا كهذه.
Maize crop in Africa,
محصول ذرة في أفريقيا،
two weeks without rain
بعد أسبوعين بلا مطر
and it's dead.
وهاهي قد ماتت.
There is a solution:
ولكن هناك حل:
resurrection plants.
النباتات القابلة للنشور.
These plants can lose 95 percent of their cellular water,
وهذه النباتات يمكن أن تخسر 95 بالمائة من الماء في خلاياها،
remain in a dry, dead-like state for months to years,
والبقاء بحالة جافة شبه ميتة لأشهر و سنوات،
and give them water,
و عندما تعطيها الماء،
they green up and start growing again.
تخضر و تبدأ النمو من جديد.
Like seeds, these are desiccation-tolerant.
و مثل البذور فهذه تتحمل الجفاف.
Like seeds, these can withstand extremes of environmental conditions.
و مثل البذور فهي تتحمل الظروف البيئية المتطرفة.
And this is a really rare phenomenon.
و هذه فعلا ظواهر نادرة.
There are only 135 flowering plant species that can do this.
و هناك فقط 135 صنفا مزهرا من النباتات يمكنها القيام بذلك.
I'm going to show you a video
ساريكم هذا القيديو
of the resurrection process of these three species
لعملية إعادة النشور لثلاثة من هذه الأنواع
in that order.
بهذا الترتيب.
And at the bottom,
و في الأسفل
there's a time axis so you can see how quickly it happens.
هناك مؤشر على الوقت وسترون سرعة حدوث ذلك.
(Applause)
(تصقيق)
Pretty amazing, huh?
مدهش جدا ، أليس كذلك؟
So I've spent the last 21 years trying to understand how they do this.
و هكذا قضيت آخر 21 عاما أحاول فهم كيف تقوم بذلك.
How do these plants dry without dying?
كيف تقوم هذه النباتات بذلك دون أن تموت؟
And I work on a variety of different resurrection plants,
و أنا أعمل على أنواع مختلفة من النباتات القابلة للنشور،
shown here in the hydrated and dry states,
تظهر هنا في حالتي الإرتواء و الجفاف،
for a number of reasons.
و لعدد من الأسباب.
One of them is that each of these plants serves as a model
أحدها إن كل واحدة من هذه النباتات تخدم كنموذج
for a crop that I'd like to make drought-tolerant.
لمحصول أريد منه أن يصبح مقاوما للجفاف.
So on the extreme top left, for example, is a grass,
وبذلك مثلا في الجانب العلوي الى اليسار ترون العشب،
it's called Eragrostis nindensis,
ويسمى (إيراغروستس نيندينسس)،
it's got a close relative called Eragrostis tef --
و له قريب اسمه (إيرافروستيس تيف) __
a lot of you might know it as "teff" --
الذي يعرفه الكثيرون باسم "الدخن" --
it's a staple food in Ethiopia,
و هو غذاء رئيسي في إيثيوبيا،
it's gluten-free,
و خالي من "الغلوتين"،
and it's something we would like to make drought-tolerant.
و هو شيء نود أن نجعله مقاوما للجفاف.
The other reason for looking at a number of plants,
والسبب الآخر للنظر إلى عدد من النباتات،
is that, at least initially,
على الأقل بشكل ابتدائي
I wanted to find out: do they do the same thing?
لأنني أردت معرفة هل تقوم هي بنفس الشيء؟
Do they all use the same mechanisms
هل تستخدم جميعها نفس الآليات
to be able to lose all that water and not die?
لتكون قابلة على فقدان كل الماء و لا تموت؟
So I undertook what we call a systems biology approach
لذلك انبعت ما يسمى بطريقة النظام الحيوي
in order to get a comprehensive understanding
لغرض الحصول على الفهم الشامل
of desiccation tolerance,
لتحمل الجفاف،
in which we look at everything
حيث ننظر إلى كل شيء
from the molecular to the whole plant, ecophysiological level.
من التركيب الجزيئي إلى مستوى الطبيعة البيئة.
For example we look at things like
مثلا ننظر إلى أشياء مثل
changes in the plant anatomy as they dried out
التغيرات في الهيكل الداخلي للنبات عندما يجف
and their ultrastructure.
وبنائه الخارجي.
We look at the transcriptome, which is just a term for a technology
و ننظر في تركيبتها الداخلية التي هي عبارة تعني التكنولوجيا
in which we look at the genes
التي ننظر من خلالها إلى الجينات
that are switched on or off, in response to drying.
التي تنشط لتعمل أو تقف كرد فعل للجفاف.
Most genes will code for proteins, so we look at the proteome.
و معظم الجينات هي شفرة للبروتينات أي إننا سننظر للبروتينات.
What are the proteins made in response to drying?
ما هي البروتينات الناتجة كأستجابة للجفاف؟
Some proteins would code for enzymes which make metabolites,
بعض البروتينات تكون شفرة للأنزيمات التي تفعّل الأيض،
so we look at the metabolome.
وعليه فإننا ننظر في جزئيات الأيض.
Now, this is important because plants are stuck in the ground.
والآن فهذا مهم لأن النباتات ملتصقة بالأرض.
They use what I call a highly tuned chemical arsenal
وهي تستخدم ما أسميه ترسانة كيميائية متناغمة جدا
to protect themselves from all the stresses of their environment.
تحميها جيدا من كل ضغوط بيئتها.
So it's important that we look
لذلك فمن المهم أن ننظر
at the chemical changes involved in drying.
للمتغيرات الكيميائية المرتبطة بالجفاف.
And at the last study that we do at the molecular level,
وفي آخر الدراسة التي نقوم بها على المستوى الجزيئي،
we look at the lipidome --
هي التغيرات الدهنية --
the lipid changes in response to drying.
وهي التغيرات الحاصلة استجابة للجفاف.
And that's also important
و هذا مهم كذلك
because all biological membranes are made of lipids.
لأن كل الأغشية الحيوية مصنوعة من الدهون.
They're held as membranes because they're in water.
و هي متماسكة لأنها في الماء.
Take away the water, those membranes fall apart.
و لو أخذنا الماء بعيدا عنها فستتساقط هذه الغشية
Lipids also act as signals to turn on genes.
والدهون تعمل كإشارات لتشغيل الجينات.
Then we use physiological and biochemical studies
لذلك نستخدم الدراسات الطبيعية والكيميائية الحيوية
to try and understand the function of the putative protectants
لمحاولة فهم وظيفة الحمايات المفترضة
that we've actually discovered in our other studies.
التي اكتشفناها فعلا في دراساتنا الأخرى.
And then use all of that to try and understand
ثم استخدام كل ذلك لمحاولة فهم
how the plant copes with its natural environment.
كيفية تعامل النبات مع بيئته الطبيعية.
I've always had the philosophy that I needed a comprehensive understanding
وكان لدي دائما فكرة حاجتي إلى الفهم الشاكل
of the mechanisms of desiccation tolerance
لآليات مقاومة الجفاف
in order to make a meaningful suggestion for a biotic application.
من أجل إقتراحات ذات معنى في التطبيثات الحيوية.
I'm sure some of you are thinking,
أنا متأكدة من أن بعضكم يفكر،
"By biotic application,
"بأن تعبير التطبيقات الحيوية،
does she mean she's going to make genetically modified crops?"
هل هي تعني بأنها ستعمل بعض النباتات المحسنة جينيا؟"
And the answer to that question is:
و الجواب على هذا السؤال هو:
depends on your definition of genetic modification.
يعتمد على مفهومكم للتحسين الجيني.
All of the crops that we eat today, wheat, rice and maize,
إن كل المحاصيل التي نأكلها اليوم كالقمح والرز والذرة،
are highly genetically modified from their ancestors,
تم تحسينها جينيا من قبل أسلافها،
but we don't consider them GM
لكننا لا نعتبرها محسنة جينيا
because they're being produced by conventional breeding.
لأن إنتاجها يتم بالطريقة التقليدية.
If you mean, am I going to put resurrection plant genes into crops,
أما إذا كنتم تعنون، هل سأضع جينات نشور النباتات في المحاصل،
your answer is yes.
فالجواب هو نعم:
In the essence of time, we have tried that approach.
و مع مرور الزمن، جربنا هذه الطريقة.
More appropriately, some of my collaborators at UCT,
و بالفعل فإن بعض المتعاونين معي من جامعة كيب تاون،
Jennifer Thomson, Suhail Rafudeen,
جنيفر و تومسون و سهيل رافدين،
have spearheaded that approach
تقدموا في هذا الطريق
and I'm going to show you some data soon.
و سأريكم بعض البيانات قريبا.
But we're about to embark upon an extremely ambitious approach,
ولكننا على وشك أن نبدأ طريقا طموحا جدا،
in which we aim to turn on whole suites of genes
نأمل فيه تفعيل مجموعات كاملة من الجينات
that are already present in every crop.
الموجودة فعلا في كل محصول.
They're just never turned on under extreme drought conditions.
وهي لم تنشط سابقا في ظروف الجفاف المفرطة.
I leave it up to you to decide
و أترك لكم القرار
whether those should be called GM or not.
هل ستسمى هذه محسنة جينيا أم لا.
I'm going to now just give you some of the data from that first approach.
و سأعطيكم الآن بعض البيانات من الطريقة الأولى.
And in order to do that
و لغرض القيام بذلك
I have to explain a little bit about how genes work.
عليّ أن أشرح كيف تقوم الجينات بعملها.
So you probably all know
و كما قد تعرفون جميعا
that genes are made of double-stranded DNA.
الجينات هي خيطين مزدوج من خيوط الحامض النووي.
It's wound very tightly into chromosomes
وهي ملتفة بقوة بشكل كروموسومات
that are present in every cell of your body or in a plant's body.
موجودة في كل خلية من جسمكم أو جسم النبات.
If you unwind that DNA, you get genes.
وإذا فككنا الحامض النووي سنحصل على الجينات.
And each gene has a promoter,
و لكل جين مشغّل،
which is just an on-off switch,
وهو عبارة عن مفتاح تشغيل-عدم تشغيل:
the gene coding region,
و منطقة شفرة الجين،
and then a terminator,
و ناهي،
which indicates that this is the end of this gene, the next gene will start.
يؤشر نهاية الجين و بداية الجين التالي.
Now, promoters are not simple on-off switches.
والمشغّل ليس مفتاح تشغيل-عدم تشغيل بسيط.
They normally require a lot of fine-tuning,
ويحتاج عادة إلى الكثير من الضبط الدقيق،
lots of things to be present and correct before that gene is switched on.
كلزوم حضور و صحة كثير من الأشياء قبل تشغيل الجين.
So what's typically done in biotech studies
وما يتم اعتياديا في الدراسات التكنوحيوية
is that we use an inducible promoter,
هو أننا نستخدم مشغّلا مقدما من قبلنا،
we know how to switch it on.
تعرف كيفية تشغيله.
We couple that to genes of interest
و نربط هذا بالجينات التي تهمنا
and put that into a plant and see how the plant responds.
و نضع ذلك في نبتة و نرى كيف تستجيب تلك النبتة.
In the study that I'm going to talk to you about,
و في الدراسة التي سأتكلم عنها،
my collaborators used a drought-induced promoter,
وضع معاونيّ مشغلا يعمل بالجفاف،
which we discovered in a resurrection plant.
اكتشفناه في نبات مقاوم للجفاف.
The nice thing about this promoter is that we do nothing.
واللطيف في هذا المشغّل إننا لا نفعل شيئا.
The plant itself senses drought.
حيث بستشعر النبات نفسه الجفاف.
And we've used it to drive antioxidant genes from resurrection plants.
واستخدمناه لوضع جينات مضادة الأكسدة من نباتات قابلة للنشور.
Why antioxidant genes?
لماذا جينات مضادة للأكسدة؟
Well, all stresses, particularly drought stress,
حسنا، إن جميع الضغوط و خاصة ضغوط الجفاف،
results in the formation of free radicals,
تتسبب في تشكيل جذور حرة،
or reactive oxygen species,
أو أصناف أوكسجينية فعالة،
which are highly damaging and can cause crop death.
و هي ضارة جدا و يمكن أن تسبب موت المحصول.
What antioxidants do is stop that damage.
وما تفعله مضادات الأكسدة هو إسقاف هذا الضرر.
So here's some data from a maize strain that's very popularly used in Africa.
وهنا بعض البيانات من نوع من الذرة الشائع جدا في افريقيا.
To the left of the arrow are plants without the genes,
إلى اليسار من السهم نباتات بدون الجينات،
to the right --
و إلى اليمين --
plants with the antioxidant genes.
نباتات مع الجينات المضادة للأكسدة.
After three weeks without watering,
و بعد ثلاثة أسابيع بدون السقي،
the ones with the genes do a hell of a lot better.
فإن التي بالجينات تبلي أحسن كثيرا.
Now to the final approach.
و الآن إلى الأسلوب الأخير.
My research has shown that there's considerable similarity
أظهر بحثي أن هناك تشابها كبيرا
in the mechanisms of desiccation tolerance in seeds and resurrection plants.
بين آليات مقاومة الجفاف في البذور و النباتات القابلة للنشور.
So I ask the question,
لذا أسأل هذا السؤال،
are they using the same genes?
هل يستخدمان نفس الجينات؟
Or slightly differently phrased,
أو بعبارة أخرى،
are resurrection plants using genes evolved in seed desiccation tolerance
هل تستخدم النباتات القابلة للنشور جينات تطورت كما في البذور المقاومة للجفاف
in their roots and leaves?
في جذورها و أوراقها؟
Have they retasked these seed genes
هل غيّرت من مهمات جينات هذه البذور
in roots and leaves of resurrection plants?
في جذور و أوراق النباتات القابلة للنشور؟
And I answer that question,
وأنا أجيب عن ذلك السؤال،
as a consequence of a lot of research from my group
على أساس الكثير من البحوث من مجموعتي
and recent collaborations from a group of Henk Hilhorst in the Netherlands,
والتعاون الأخير مع مجموعة هينك هلهورست في هولندا،
Mel Oliver in the United States
و ميل أوليفر في الولايات المتحدة
and Julia Buitink in France.
و جوليا بويتنك في فرنسا.
The answer is yes,
و الجواب هو نعم،
that there is a core set of genes that are involved in both.
وهو أن هناك مجموعة أساسية من الجينات تشترك في الاثنين.
And I'm going to illustrate this very crudely for maize,
و سوف أشرح بشكل عام ما يحصل للذرة،
where the chromosomes below the off switch
حيث تمثل الكروموسومات تحت مفتاح إيقاف التشغيل
represent all the genes that are required for desiccation tolerance.
جميع الجينات المطلوبة لتحمل الجفاف.
So as maize seeds dried out at the end of their period of development,
وما أن تجف بذور الذرة بعد نهاية فترة نموها،
they switch these genes on.
حتى يتم تشغيل هذه الجينات.
Resurrection plants switch on the same genes
و تشغل النباتات القابلة للنشور نفس الجينات
when they dry out.
عندما تجف تماما.
All modern crops, therefore,
وهكذا، فجميع المحاصيل العصرية،
have these genes in their roots and leaves,
لديها جميع الجينات في جذورها و أوراقها،
they just never switch them on.
ولكنها فقط لا تشغلها.
They only switch them on in seed tissues.
و هي تشغلها فقط في أغشية بذورها.
So what we're trying to do right now
لذلك فإن ما نحاول عمله الآن
is to understand the environmental and cellular signals
هو فهم المحيط و إشارات الخلايا
that switch on these genes in resurrection plants,
التي تشغل هذه الجينات في النباتات القابلة للنشور،
to mimic the process in crops.
لمحاكاة هذه العملية في المحاصيل.
And just a final thought.
و فكرة أخيرة فقط.
What we're trying to do very rapidly
ما نحاول عمله بسرعة عالية
is to repeat what nature did in the evolution of resurrection plants
هو إعادة عمل الطبيعة عند تطور النباتات القابلة للنشور
some 10 to 40 million years ago.
قبل 40 أو 50 مليون سنة.
My plants and I thank you for your attention.
أنا و نباتاتي نشكركم على إنتباهكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)